<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-28T13:00:49+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website for Ryan Slocum </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Discrete vs Continuous Skills</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/discrete-vs-continuous-skills/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discrete vs Continuous Skills"/><published>2024-03-09T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-09T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/discrete-vs-continuous-skills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/discrete-vs-continuous-skills/"><![CDATA[<p>A week ago, a friend of mine took me skateboarding for the first time. I was convinced (as was he) that I would hate it, but it turned out to be a really fun time! During the hour and a half I spent learning the basics of how to balance and push on the board, I realized that what I was really enjoying was the feeling of learning, and the sense of accomplishment that comes with. This realization was accompanied by the thought that there is a division of hobbies in my mind: those with discrete progressions, and those with continuous progression. Recently, I’ve been primarily engaged in the latter, but this skating excursion made me realize that I would do well to practice balance between the two.</p> <h4 id="discrete-vs-continuous-progressions">Discrete vs Continuous Progressions</h4> <p>In my mind, the difference between these two categories is in where the effort of progression lies. For continuous progression skills, it’s very easy to get started, but harder to get good. For discrete progressions, it’s harder to start, but mastery comes easily after.</p> <p>As an example, I’ll compare two of my hobbies as of late: weightlifting and juggling. To progress in weightlifting, there are two main steps: learn how to execute the lift properly, then progressively add weight to the lift. I would argue that by far, the harder part of this progression is adding more weight over time. Saying you’ve “mastered” a lift can take years, depending on what your benchmark is.</p> <p>However, with juggling, the opposite is true. It’s significantly harder to learn how to do the skill, but once you have it, it becomes easier and easier to execute it more fluidly. For example, with a five-ball cascade, it took me months to get to the point where I could “juggle” the pattern–meaning 10 catches–but after that point, it was relatively easy to continue on to 100 catches. The hardest step was learning to execute the skill properly, whereas mastery can come shortly afterwards.</p> <p>The other element of discrete skills is a fundamental difference in steps of progression. In executing a squat with good form, there should be no real difference in lifting the bar or 315 pounds. However, there is a clear dividing line between being able to juggle a five ball cascade and not. A counter example I considered was bouldering, where the grades are definitely discretized, and climbing a V5 feels like a clear advancement over climbing a V4. But I would still call this a continuous skill, because there is not a fundamental difference between the skills or strength needed to execute these climbs.</p> <p>While my definition of the line between these two types of skills is definitely shakey, there are lots of skills I can think of that fall into one of these two buckets. I’ve tried to categorize some of the ones I dabble in below:</p> <p><strong>Skills with discrete progression:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Juggling</li> <li>Skateboarding</li> <li>Calisthenics</li> <li>Bike maintainance</li> <li>Coding</li> </ul> <p><strong>Skills with continuous progression:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Weightlifting</li> <li>Running</li> <li>Bouldering/Climbing</li> <li>Writing</li> <li>Language Learning</li> </ul> <h4 id="why-does-this-matter">Why does this matter?</h4> <p>It doesn’t, really. I just think it’s an interesting way to think about skills and mastery. I do think it would be good to make sure you’re involved with both–learning can be complicated, and having outlets in your life that give you both a sense of continuous improvement and the feeling of learning new skills is probably a good way to maintain balance.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Categorizing skills and hobbies by progression type]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing Digital Distraction</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/managing-digital-distractions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing Digital Distraction"/><published>2024-02-17T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-17T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/managing-digital-distractions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/managing-digital-distractions/"><![CDATA[<p>I am currently reading an excellent book called <em>Stolen Focus</em> by Johann Hari. Hari writes about the topic of focus: what it means to be focused, why our ability to focus has been declining over recent years, and what we can do about it. I am only halfway through the book, but I have found it both fascinating and worrying, and it’s got me thinking about the ways that I can cut back on technological distractions. Below are some of the strategies I’ve tried to reduce the unfulfilling time I spend on screens.</p> <h4 id="deleting-snapchat">Deleting Snapchat</h4> <p>The first step I can remember taking towards reducing digital distractions was deleting Snapchat towards the end of high school. I had used Snapchat for the previous four years, and it served as my primary method of communication with my friends. However, the immediacy of of the platform was really harful for me. I was able to see what people were up to at any moment, using both their stories and the maps. That, in combination with the garbage content that fills the stories screen, was enough to get me to delete the app. It had an immediate effect on my mental health, and I have never regretted the decision.</p> <h4 id="deleting-apps-in-favor-of-websites">Deleting apps in favor of websites</h4> <p>One of the steps I took in my first year of college was deleting the Youtube, LinkedIn, and Instagram apps from my phone. I still wanted to be on these platforms, but a less useable interface and more log-in friction helped me to limit my time spent on them. This worked very well for each of these platforms, especially combined with the fact that I always use private browsing, which doesn’t remember my log-in information.</p> <h4 id="apple-notification-settings">Apple Notification Settings</h4> <p>Recently, I have been experimenting with the notification settings on my iPhone. Apple allows <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/change-notification-settings-iph7c3d96bab/ios">relatively fine-grain control</a> over what apps can give notifications, what those notifications can look and sound like, and when they can appear. Over the last couple months, I’ve been racheting down the notifications my phone can give me. I started by removing the vibrations and tones from many apps, and preventing most notifications from showing up on the lock screen. These changes made me realize how little value many notifications provide, so I ended up removing some entirely.</p> <p>Most recently, I adjusted the settings so that the only notifications that can show up on my lock screen are text messages, and only phone calls can make my phone vibrate. These changes came after a realization that when I’m in conversation and my phone buzzes in my pocket, part of my attention wanders to what the message could be. It’s nearly always unimportant, and I figure that if someone needs to, they can always call me.</p> <h4 id="screen-time-limits">Screen Time Limits</h4> <p>One experiment that was more or less a failure for me was Apple’s screen time limits. These should prevent you from spending more than the allotted amount of daily time on an app, but in practice, they work better as a form of parental control. Almost every time the time limit came up for me when watching Youtube or browsing Instagram, I would simply dismiss it and continue scrolling. The only app I’ve found this to be helpful for is Strava, where I have a ten-minute daily limit set up. Because Strava is so non-addictive compared to other social platforms, the limit serves as more of a gentle reminder that I should be doing something else with my time.</p> <p>These screen time limits can definitely be useful, but they don’t fit my needs, mostly because I don’t want to rely on someone else to keep the code that locks the screen time settings.</p> <h4 id="password-managers">Password managers</h4> <p>In an effort to further limit my useage of Instagram, I had my laptop’s password manager generate a random password for my account, which I have not memorized. Because I don’t know the password, this prevents me from logging on using my phone, and so I won’t spend half an hour scrolling through reels in bed. I can now only use Instagram on my laptop, which I don’t do often, so this allows me to continue using the platform to keep up with friends, but without falling victim to the algorithm. This is sort of an unconventional step, but I’ve found it works very well.</p> <h4 id="youtube-personalization-settings">Youtube personalization settings</h4> <p>In the last six months, Youtube has absolutely been my worst time sink. I’d get sucked in for hours on end, convincing myself that I was learning something, but really just wasting a lot of time. I thought that this problem had to be solved by pure will, because I still wanted to be able to use Youtube to look up tutorials for school and work, and to enjoy high-quality, long-form entertainment. I also couldn’t use the same tricks I had used above, because I use my Google account everywhere, for all sorts of things.</p> <p>However, last week my friend told me that you can completely <a href="https://support.google.com/youtube/answer/95725">remove personalization from Youtube</a>, along with all your previous watch history. This would mean that Youtube would have nothing to recommend to me except for the channels I was subscribed to. I tried it out, and it’s been amazing. Over the last week, I’ve spent so much more time reading because of this change alone.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>I’ve found these tricks very helpful in limiting my screentime, although it took a lot of experimenting to find strategies that worked. Maybe you’ll find one of them helpful yourself!</p> <p>I do think that the manipulative design of free platforms like Instagram, Youtube, and Snapchat is concerning, so I am going to continue to explore ways I can limit my exposure to them, while tapping into the benefits they offer. If you want to learn more about the topic, I would absolutely recommend <em>Stolen Focus</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology,"/><category term="reading"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Steps I've taken to improve my digital life]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Outdoor Adventure Films</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/adventure-films/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Outdoor Adventure Films"/><published>2024-02-02T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/adventure-films</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/adventure-films/"><![CDATA[<p>Whenever I’m feeling lazy, down, or unmotivated, I love to watch outdoor adventure films, usually featuring some endurance sport. For a while, I was binging ultramarathon race documentaries. Then FKT attempts. Sometimes bikepacking films.</p> <p>Watching these sorts of films serves as a form of escapism and provides inspiration for future trips and challenges. Many are also beautifully-made pieces of art as well, that I’m sure anyone would enjoy.</p> <p>Below, I’ve outlined a couple of my favorites, in case you’d like to check them out:</p> <h3 id="rei-presents-how-to-run-100-miles"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iC7Lh4opLsc">REI Presents: How To Run 100 Miles</a></h3> <p>For reasons I can’t quite put into words, this is my favorite ultramarathon film. It’s short, it’s well-made, and it has brought me nearly to tears every time I’ve watched it. I also really like the creative flairs that shine through throughout the film. There’s a quote somewhere halfway through that I think about whenever I’m doing something challenging: “When you just keep pushing the bar of the hardest thing you’ve ever done further and further out, then all those hard things become way less hard.”</p> <h3 id="trials-of-miles"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E6TbeiKxpSs">Trials of Miles</a></h3> <p>Beau Miles is a favorite of mine on Youtube, and he has a several adventure films on his channel. <em>Trials of Miles</em> documents his journey through the Australian Alps, trying to set a FKT. I think that the logistics of attempts like this are fascinating, so it’s great to see in more detail how he is supported by his family and friends on the run.</p> <h3 id="a-bivvy-a-phone-and-a-drone-cycling-home-from-china"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mmdxs_0yYwc">A bivvy, a phone and a drone: cycling home from China.</a></h3> <p>This documentary is short but very impressive. Josh Reid does an excellent job of self-filming his journey from China to the UK, not to mention his insane feat of biking over 200km a day for months on end. The drone shots give an impressive view of the landscape. My only complaint about this film is that I wish it were longer!</p> <h3 id="biking-borders"><a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/81405382">Biking Borders</a></h3> <p>Also about a transcontinental bike ride, <em>Biking Borders</em> features two German men who ride from Berlin to Beijing, raising money for education along the way. I really love how much the film focuses on the human element of the journey, featuring heavily the hospitality the bikepackers received throughout Eastern Europe and Central Asia.</p> <h3 id="bass-by-kayak"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KZaFo00Hel8">Bass by Kayak</a></h3> <p>Also from Beau Miles, <em>Bass by Kayak</em> is different from the others on this list in that it documents a sea kayaking journey, from mainland Australia to Tasmania. Watching Beau navigate the Bass Strait was my first time learning about sea kayaking, and seeing the possibility of journeys like this has definitely made me want to try it out myself someday.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="outdoors,"/><category term="running"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite guilty pleasure]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I Ran My First Ultramarathon</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/how-i-ran-my-first-ultra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I Ran My First Ultramarathon"/><published>2024-01-28T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/how-i-ran-my-first-ultra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/how-i-ran-my-first-ultra/"><![CDATA[<p>I decided in early October that I wanted to run a race in December, but I couldn’t find any marathons or half marathons that looked particularly appealing in Colorado. However, there were two 50ks to choose from in early December, and one of them was trail race. So I decided I would sign up for the <a href="https://humanpotentialrunning.com/sawmill/">Sawmill 50k</a> in Stauton State Park for my first trail race, as well as my first ultramarathon.</p> <h3 id="training">Training</h3> <p>I didn’t have a defined training program for this race, as I was motivated more by the experience than a target time. I worked my way up from 30 miles per week (mpw) in earlier September to 50 mpw, focusing on getting on trails as often as I could. Usually four of my five runs each week were on the trails, and I tried to target at least 1k ft of vertical ascent for each run as well. Because the race would have over 5k ft of vert, I wanted to be sure I was ready for the elevation change.</p> <p>I tried to build in a couple checkpoints in my training to convince myself I was on track for a 50k. The first was an <a href="https://strava.app.link/S0YViojUJGb">11 mile run</a> in late October, where I got in around 2k ft of vert, seeing if I was be comfortable with that average grade for a longer run. It felt great, especially after doing so much running on steeper terrain.</p> <p>In late November, <a href="https://strava.app.link/9x34W8bUJGb">I ran up Mt. Baldy</a> in Bozeman, MT, for 4.5k ft of vert, which was a personal record for me at the time. Two days later, <a href="https://strava.app.link/7gxjdxfUJGb">I ran 16 miles</a> on much flatter terrain, trying to stay on trails as much as I could. The combination of these two runs made me feel like I was prepared for both the distance and the elevation the race would entail.</p> <h3 id="race-day-preparation">Race day preparation</h3> <p>Up until the day of the race, it wasn’t clear whether it was going to snow or not, so I packed everything I needed for colder weather and snow on the trails. It turned out to be a pretty dry day, so I didn’t end up using half of what I brought. Here’s what I carried with me during the race, knowing that we’d get to come back to the start twice before the end of the race:</p> <ul> <li>Clothing: <ul> <li>Trail running shoes</li> <li>Running tights</li> <li>Micro-grid base layer</li> <li>Light windbreaker</li> <li>8-liter trail running vest</li> <li>Sunglasses, hat, gloves</li> </ul> </li> <li>Fuel: <ul> <li>Two 500ml soft flasks (one with Tailwind Endurance mix, the other with water)</li> <li>Baggie of fun-sized Snickers</li> <li>Two GU energy gels</li> </ul> </li> <li>Extras: <ul> <li>Instant hand-warmers</li> <li>Extra gloves</li> <li>Space-blanket, just in case</li> <li>Yak-trax (just for the section that was icy)</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>My stroke of genius for this race was to buy fun-sized snickers bars, take all the wrappers off the night before, and portion them into bags of about 500 calories each. This made them easier to eat and keep track of my calories, and I didn’t have to worry about littering accidentally on the trail.</p> <h3 id="race-day"><a href="https://strava.app.link/MS45ewoUJGb">Race day</a></h3> <h5 id="start">Start</h5> <p>The race started at 7, so I didn’t need a headlamp. There were three laps, the first being about 15 miles, and the other two around 8 miles. It was a small crowd, with only 30-40 people racing the 50k. When we started, my goal was to hang on to the lead pack for as long as I could, just to see what kind of pace they set. So after the first mile, there were about 5 of us out in front, and we settled into the first hill.</p> <p>This first ascent showed me that it really is okay to walk during an ultra. Everyone walked up this first incline, many taking the opportunity to shed some layers. By the time we reached the top, I was running with a bearded guy named Dave. I asked him about his ultra experience, and it turned out he had an incredible resume. He had run six 100-milers, and had just run the Moab 240 a few months earlier. He was kind enough to give me some tips on pacing, and I learned that we lived not too far from each other in Boulder.</p> <p>Around mile 9, I was feeling really good, and we were beginning a descent. So I decided I would set my own pace, and left Dave to go a little faster. It felt really good to go downhill, and soon enough I was back at the start, having run about half the race. However, I had known before that this would be the easiest part by far, so I was careful to make sure I was fueling the appropriate amount. With the help of my parents, who were kind enough to come out and support me, I got in and out of the aid station in just a couple minutes, ready to start lap 2 and another big climb.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/stauton_state_park-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/stauton_state_park-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/stauton_state_park-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sawmill50k/stauton_state_park.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Stauton State Park was beautiful! A great place for a trail race. </div> <h5 id="lap-2">Lap 2</h5> <p>This second lap was challenging, but still felt good. I was running alone, but managed to maintain a good pace, especially on the downhill sections. During this lap, I passed three records: my longest run that year (16 miles), my longest run ever (26.2 miles), and the most vert I had ever ascended in a run (~4.5k ft). These accomplishments gave me a lot of confidence going into the third lap, along with the fact that I was still in the lead.</p> <h5 id="final-lap">Final lap</h5> <p>Heading out of aid station for a third time, my parents had warned me that it was going to get a lot windier, so I put my hat and gloves back on. A mile in, I had to ask a very nice couple on the trails if they would open my handwarmers for me, because I had lost all my finger dexterity with the windchill. I was really glad I brought those, because they kept my fingers functional for the last 10km of the race.</p> <p>I walked nearly all of that final uphill, something around 1k ft of vert. I was really tired at this point, but knew I could finish out the race if I could get to the top. It was also a struggle to keep eating and drinking, but I managed to get down another few snickers bars in this lap, as well as plenty of water.</p> <p>By the time I crested the last hill, I had about four miles to go. I set a good pace on the downhill, walking every now and then to eat and rest my quads. In the last two miles, I realized I could break six hours if I really went for it, so I gave it a good effort. When I crossed the finish line, I had a time just over six hours, which the timekeeper recorded as 6:00:00 (yay!).</p> <p>At the end of the race, I was really craving anything savory, so I had a quesadilla and some avocado. I waited around to see the people I had chatted with during the race finish, then my parents took me out for some pizza at a place down the road. It was a pretty great day.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/lap3-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/lap3-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/lap3-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sawmill50k/lap3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/finisher-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/finisher-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/sawmill50k/finisher-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sawmill50k/finisher.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Managed to finish still smiling! </div> <h3 id="what-i-learned">What I learned</h3> <p>Being new at this sport, there was a lot that could have gone wrong. But because the weather was great, my fitness was decent, and the race was very well put-together, it all went fairly seamlessly! Here are some of the things I would change next time:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Bring some savory food:</strong> I was really struggling to eat by the end of the race because I had only brought sugary stuff. Next time, I’m bringing a sandwhich, preferably with some bacon.</li> <li><strong>Better pacing:</strong> My first lap was likely way too fast, especially when compared to the third lap. It felt good, but it would have been better to leave more in reserve for the second half.</li> <li><strong>Stop and enjoy it!</strong> I think being out front had me running in fear a bit, especially later in the race. It would’ve been nice to stop now and then and enjoy the view.</li> </ol> <p>Overall, it was a great experience! First trail race, first ultra, and first time I’ve ever won a race. Thanks to Human Potential Running for putting on a fun race. I definitely plan to do another ultra sometime soon, along with other trail races.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="running,"/><category term="outdoors"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My experience at the Sawmill 50k]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New-semester resolutions</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/new-semester-resolutions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New-semester resolutions"/><published>2024-01-21T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-21T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/new-semester-resolutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/new-semester-resolutions/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve never been a big believer in New Year’s resolutions. Whenever the end of December rolls around, I generally feel some mix of annoyance and confusion towards the throngs of people settings goals that, research has shown, will almost certainly not come to fruition. The rationale behind my annoyance is simple: it seems to me that if you truly want to achieve a goal, you would start right away, not at some arbitrary point in the future when the last digit in the year turns over.</p> <p>However, in saying this I also feel like a hypocrite. I love setting goals for when a new semester starts. I’m currently a student at CU, where I am graduating in May. With the beginning of every semester, I love to go through the things that have worked well in the past, and make both refinements and more radical changes. However, this feels like a fundamentally different goal-setting mentality to me. Because there is a concrete change in my life due to a shift in class schedule, content, and workload, every new semester presents an opportunity to break out of old habits and create new ones.</p> <p>As I’m coming to the end of my college career, I’m realizing that these opportunities to change my behavior might come less frequently than they have been. Currently, I have at least three opportunities a year to effectively redefine how I spend my time. When my peers and I enter the workforce, these opportunities will lose their regularity, and will be predicated instead on moving cities, changing jobs, or other life-altering events.</p> <p>These events are certainly not necessary to create positive change, but they can help to anchor new habits in a different reality. So for those trying to create a new habit, consider changing something else about your life in a way that supports those goals. That could be waking up earlier or later, or moving your working hours if possible. Changing too much could lead to increased stress and failure, but the right adjustments could be helpful in tying a new habit to a new routine.</p> <p>I also see a benefit to the lack of constant disruptions in one’s schedule. If things are going well, it’s great to be able to keep them that way for longer than four months. Many semesters, I’ve found that I just reach the point where I’ve fine-tuned my habits and routines to my schedule in the final month, but all that hard work goes out the window when my classes completely rearrange. It would certainly be nice to be able to tweak and build iteratively over a longer period.</p> <p>I can’t say that I’ve had the opportunity to compare these two methods of goal-setting. I’ve been in school essentially my entire life, so I’ve always had the chance to change things up in August or January. However, I think that it’s important to consider how the lack of rapid turnover in scheduling might affect my goal-setting going forward.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I think about goal-setting in college]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My 5 favorite books of 2023</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-favorite-books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My 5 favorite books of 2023"/><published>2024-01-14T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-favorite-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-favorite-books/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite taking a sizable break mid-year, I read 41 books in 2023, making it the year I’ve read the most in my adult life. Below are my 5 favorites from this year, in the order in which I read them.</p> <h2 id="1-say-nothing-by-patrick-radden-keefe">1. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40163119-say-nothing"><em>Say Nothing</em> by Patrick Radden Keefe</a></h2> <p>Due to the fact that I was traveling to Ireland and Northern Ireland for my spring break, I was looking for a book that would fill the appreciable gap in my knowledge on the Troubles in the late 20th century. <em>Say Nothing</em> was an excellent introduction to the conflict, with the book focusing on the mysterious disappearance of Jean McConville, a resident of Belfast in the 1970s. Then story then zooms out to cover the major events of the Troubles, told through the eyes of a couple key figures deeply involved with the movement.</p> <p>What I particularly liked about this book was that it was written in such a way that I felt deeply sympathetic for the provisional IRA’s cause in the first half of the book, but was also able to see the harm caused by their methods, and the futility of their efforts approaching the 21st century. I found the book very compelling, and was sufficiently educated on the conflict after reading it to appreciate the continued tension on my visit to Belfast.</p> <h2 id="2-why-fish-dont-exist-by-lulu-miller">2. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50887097-why-fish-don-t-exist"><em>Why Fish Don’t Exist</em> by Lulu Miller</a></h2> <p>When I was asked for book recommendations this fall, <em>Why Fish Don’t Exist</em> was invariably my first suggestion. I loved this book so much that I read it all in one 5-hour sitting, unable to tear my eyes away. I don’t want to say too much about the book, because I think the twists and turns were part of what made reading it such a great experience. What I can say is that Miller does an amazing job of taking what I had originally thought was a biography, and incoporating both her personal experience and the experience of those she interviews in a way I didn’t see coming in the first third of the book. This book caused me to shed a few tears at two separate points, which is a pretty rare occurence for me.</p> <h2 id="3-thinking-in-systems-by-donella-meadows">3. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3828902-thinking-in-systems"><em>Thinking in Systems</em> by Donella Meadows</a></h2> <p><em>Thinking in Systems</em> was a close second for my most recommended book of this fall. An expert in systems thinking, Meadows lays out the fundamental components of a system, some archetypical examples of systems we encounter every day, and strategies for intervention. I thought that this book would make the perfect introduction to an engineering leadership class called Complex Leadership Challenges I took a year before. Equipping students with the basics of systems theory before setting them loose to explore a system of their choosing for the rest of the semester seemed to me a perfect recipe for positive outcomes. Although it’s a long story, discussions around this topic wound up landing me a part-time job this academic year, so I’m very glad that I read this book!</p> <h2 id="4-the-obstacle-is-the-way-by-ryan-holiday">4. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18668059-the-obstacle-is-the-way"><em>The Obstacle is the Way</em> by Ryan Holiday</a></h2> <p>When I started <em>The Obstacle is the Way</em>, I had just finished Holiday’s other book, <em>Ego is the Enemy</em>, which could be an honorable mention for this list. I found <em>The Obstacle is the Way</em> to contain especially valuable insights for this stage in my life, when I am unsure of what’s next for me after university, and afraid of the coming struggles. Holiday, distilling the learnings of the great stoic thinkers, beseeches the reader to lean into these challenges as the road to growth. While this is easy to say and hard to carry out, the examples throughout the book give concrete examples of how successful people have applied these principles to their benefit. This book really did change my outlook on life challenges and opportunities.</p> <h2 id="5-the-speed-of-dark-by-elizabeth-moon">5. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/96063.The_Speed_of_Dark"><em>The Speed of Dark</em> by Elizabeth Moon</a></h2> <p>Although this book was required reading for an engineering leadership class I took this semester called Intelligent Leadership, it was one of my favorites of the year. Told from the perspective of an autistic man named Lou in the not-too-distance future, this speculative fiction novel opened my eyes to the experiences of the neurodivergent. Though certainly not representative of the lives of all autistic people, Lou’s internal dialogue showcases a different way of experiencing the world, showcasing his concerted effort towards understanding social cues that many of us take for granted. My favorite part of this book was the classroom conversation, where my peers discussed the extent to which their experience matched Lou’s internal dialogue. For my final project in this class, I chose to write an essay in defense of the controversial epilogue of this book, defending Moon’s narrative choices.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I read 41 books in 2023. Here are my favorites!]]></summary></entry></feed>