<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-01-22T23:04:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website for Ryan Slocum </subtitle><entry><title type="html">New-semester resolutions</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-new-semester-resolutions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New-semester resolutions"/><published>2024-01-21T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-21T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-new-semester-resolutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-new-semester-resolutions/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve never been a big believer in New Year’s resolutions. Whenever the end of December rolls around, I generally feel some mix of annoyance and confusion towards the throngs of people settings goals that, research has shown, will almost certainly not come to fruition. The rationale behind my annoyance is simple: it seems to me that if you truly want to achieve a goal, you would start right away, not at some arbitrary point in the future when the last digit in the year turns over.</p> <p>However, in saying this I also feel like a hypocrite. I love setting goals for when a new semester starts. I’m currently a student at CU, where I am graduating in May. With the beginning of every semester, I love to go through the things that have worked well in the past, and make both refinements and more radical changes. However, this feels like a fundamentally different goal-setting mentality to me. Because there is a concrete change in my life due to a shift in class schedule, content, and workload, every new semester presents an opportunity to break out of old habits and create new ones.</p> <p>As I’m coming to the end of my college career, I’m realizing that these opportunities to change my behavior might come less frequently than they have been. Currently, I have at least three opportunities a year to effectively redefine how I spend my time. When my peers and I enter the workforce, these opportunities will lose their regularity, and will be predicated instead on moving cities, changing jobs, or other life-altering events.</p> <p>These events are certainly not necessary to create positive change, but they can help to anchor new habits in a different reality. So for those trying to create a new habit, consider changing something else about your life in a way that supports those goals. That could be waking up earlier or later, or moving your working hours if possible. Changing too much could lead to increased stress and failure, but the right adjustments could be helpful in tying a new habit to a new routine.</p> <p>I also see a benefit to the lack of constant disruptions in one’s schedule. If things are going well, it’s great to be able to keep them that way for longer than four months. Many semesters, I’ve found that I just reach the point where I’ve fine-tuned my habits and routines to my schedule in the final month, but all that hard work goes out the window when my classes completely rearrange. It would certainly be nice to be able to tweak and build iteratively over a longer period.</p> <p>I can’t say that I’ve had the opportunity to compare these two methods of goal-setting. I’ve been in school essentially my entire life, so I’ve always had the chance to change things up in August or January. However, I think that it’s important to consider how the lack of rapid turnover in scheduling might affect my goal-setting going forward.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I think about goal-setting in college]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My 5 favorite books of 2023</title><link href="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-favorite-books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My 5 favorite books of 2023"/><published>2024-01-14T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-favorite-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.ryanslocum.com/blog/2023-favorite-books/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite taking a sizable break mid-year, I read 41 books in 2023, making it the year I’ve read the most in my adult life. Below are my 5 favorites from this year, in the order in which I read them.</p> <h2 id="1-say-nothing-by-patrick-radden-keefe">1. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40163119-say-nothing"><em>Say Nothing</em> by Patrick Radden Keefe</a></h2> <p>Due to the fact that I was traveling to Ireland and Northern Ireland for my spring break, I was looking for a book that would fill the appreciable gap in my knowledge on the Troubles in the late 20th century. <em>Say Nothing</em> was an excellent introduction to the conflict, with the book focusing on the mysterious disappearance of Jean McConville, a resident of Belfast in the 1970s. Then story then zooms out to cover the major events of the Troubles, told through the eyes of a couple key figures deeply involved with the movement.</p> <p>What I particularly liked about this book was that it was written in such a way that I felt deeply sympathetic for the provisional IRA’s cause in the first half of the book, but was also able to see the harm caused by their methods, and the futility of their efforts approaching the 21st century. I found the book very compelling, and was sufficiently educated on the conflict after reading it to appreciate the continued tension on my visit to Belfast.</p> <h2 id="2-why-fish-dont-exist-by-lulu-miller">2. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50887097-why-fish-don-t-exist"><em>Why Fish Don’t Exist</em> by Lulu Miller</a></h2> <p>When I was asked for book recommendations this fall, <em>Why Fish Don’t Exist</em> was invariably my first suggestion. I loved this book so much that I read it all in one 5-hour sitting, unable to tear my eyes away. I don’t want to say too much about the book, because I think the twists and turns were part of what made reading it such a great experience. What I can say is that Miller does an amazing job of taking what I had originally thought was a biography, and incoporating both her personal experience and the experience of those she interviews in a way I didn’t see coming in the first third of the book. This book caused me to shed a few tears at two separate points, which is a pretty rare occurence for me.</p> <h2 id="3-thinking-in-systems-by-donella-meadows">3. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3828902-thinking-in-systems"><em>Thinking in Systems</em> by Donella Meadows</a></h2> <p><em>Thinking in Systems</em> was a close second for my most recommended book of this fall. An expert in systems thinking, Meadows lays out the fundamental components of a system, some archetypical examples of systems we encounter every day, and strategies for intervention. I thought that this book would make the perfect introduction to an engineering leadership class called Complex Leadership Challenges I took a year before. Equipping students with the basics of systems theory before setting them loose to explore a system of their choosing for the rest of the semester seemed to me a perfect recipe for positive outcomes. Although it’s a long story, discussions around this topic wound up landing me a part-time job this academic year, so I’m very glad that I read this book!</p> <h2 id="4-the-obstacle-is-the-way-by-ryan-holiday">4. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18668059-the-obstacle-is-the-way"><em>The Obstacle is the Way</em> by Ryan Holiday</a></h2> <p>When I started <em>The Obstacle is the Way</em>, I had just finished Holiday’s other book, <em>Ego is the Enemy</em>, which could be an honorable mention for this list. I found <em>The Obstacle is the Way</em> to contain especially valuable insights for this stage in my life, when I am unsure of what’s next for me after university, and afraid of the coming struggles. Holiday, distilling the learnings of the great stoic thinkers, beseeches the reader to lean into these challenges as the road to growth. While this is easy to say and hard to carry out, the examples throughout the book give concrete examples of how successful people have applied these principles to their benefit. This book really did change my outlook on life challenges and opportunities.</p> <h2 id="5-the-speed-of-dark-by-elizabeth-moon">5. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/96063.The_Speed_of_Dark"><em>The Speed of Dark</em> by Elizabeth Moon</a></h2> <p>Although this book was required reading for an engineering leadership class I took this semester called Intelligent Leadership, it was one of my favorites of the year. Told from the perspective of an autistic man named Lou in the not-too-distance future, this speculative fiction novel opened my eyes to the experiences of the neurodivergent. Though certainly not representative of the lives of all autistic people, Lou’s internal dialogue showcases a different way of experiencing the world, showcasing his concerted effort towards understanding social cues that many of us take for granted. My favorite part of this book was the classroom conversation, where my peers discussed the extent to which their experience matched Lou’s internal dialogue. For my final project in this class, I chose to write an essay in defense of the controversial epilogue of this book, defending Moon’s narrative choices.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I read 41 books in 2023. Here are my favorites!]]></summary></entry></feed>